Joaquin Miller Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Joaquin Miller Collection
1870-1931
YCAL MSS 861
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.42
(3 boxes)
Miller, Joaquin, 1837-1913
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired from various sources. For more information see catalog cards filed in the collection.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Correspondence, 1871-1931. II. Writings, 1870-1905. III. Other Papers, 1872-1901.
Joaquin Miller (1837-1913)
Joaquin Miller (1837-1913), American poet.
Scope and Contents
The collection is comprised of correspondence, writings, photographs, and printed material documenting the life and career of American poet Joaquin Miller. Correspondence consists of Miller's outgoing letters; recipients include friends, family, editors, and publishers. Autographs -- one of which is signed on a photograph -- are part of the correspondence. The collection includes correspondence and clippings sent from Joaquin Miller's daughter, Juanita Joaquina Miller, to Laura Stedman. Autograph manuscripts and page proofs of several of Miller's poems can be found in the collection. Drafts of Miller's writings and correspondence with publishers provides insight into his creative process and experience publishing. A printer's copy of Miller's poem "Rough Times in Idaho" is notable because it is written in the hand of author Ina Donna Coolbrith and corrected by author Bret Harte (who published the poem in The Overland Monthly ).
American literature -- 19th century; American literature -- West (U.S.); Authors, American -- 19th century -- Archives; Poets, American -- 19th century -- Archives; Photographs -- United States -- 19th century; Photographic prints -- United States -- 19th century; Authors -- United States -- 19th century; Poets -- United States -- 19th century; Coolbrith, Ina D. (Ina Donna), 1841-1928; Harte, Bret, 1836-1902; Miller, Juanita Joaquina, 1880-1970; Miller, Joaquin, 1837-1913; Stedman, Laura, 1881-1939
- Correspondence, 1871-1931; Series I
  Arrangement
  Series I is arranged alphabetically by recipient.
  - Alger, Abbie, 2 autograph letters, signed, Washington, 1883 November 21, undated (Box 1)
  - "Babes in the woods," 1 autograph letter, signed, to "my dear babes in the woods," The Hights, California, 1894 January 14 (Box 1)
  - Bliss, ---, 1 autograph letter signed, to "My dear Bliss," London, 1875 April 8 (Box 1)
  - Carmany, John H., 5 autograph letters, signed, 1872 July 12-September 6 (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Removed from Songs of the Sunlands, 1873.
  - Century, editors, 1 autograph letter, signed, The Hights, Dimond, California, 1906 April 5 (Box 1)
  - Conway, ---, 1 autograph letter, signed, Boston, Massachusetts, 1873(?) September 13 (Box 1)
  - The Critic, editors, 1 autograph letter, signed, San Francisco, with manuscript corrections and directions to the printer by the editors of The Critic, 1886 September 9 (Box 1)
  - File, Franklin, 1 autograph letter, signed, Oakland, California, 1890 July 20 (Box 1)
  - Hall, Gertrude, 1 autograph letter, signed, Oakland, California, 1888 August (Box 1)
  - The Independent, 1 autograph letter, signed, London, 1875 April 8 (Box 1)
  - Johns, ---, 1 autograph letter, signed, Dimond, California, 1904(?) May 8 (Box 1)
  - Kervy, H.P., 1 autograph letter, signed, Oakland, California, with addressed, stamped envelope, 1887 August 13 (Box 1)
  - Leland, Abigail, 1 autograph letter, signed, New Orleans, 188(?) February 21 (Box 1)
  - Life, editor, 1 autograph letter, signed, to the editor of Life, Washington, D.C., 1885 April (Box 1)
  - Mcall, ---, 1 autograph letter, signed, New York, 1882 January 25 (Box 1)
  - Miller, Dewitt, 1 autograph letter, signed, Oakland, California, 1892 October 20 (Box 1)
  - Niles, ---, 2 autograph letters, signed, New York, New York, 1879 November 17, undated (Box 1)
  - The Overland Monthly, editor, 2 autograph letters, signed, New York City and London, 1871-1872 (Box 1)
  - Roberts Brothers, 1 autograph letter, signed, Oakland, California, 1881(7?) August 6 (Box 1)
  - Roosevelt, Theodore,1 autograph letter, signed, Washington, D.C., 1887, 1903 (Box 1)
    Includes 1 autograph letter, signed, to "my dear boy," one of Theodore Roosevelt's sons, April 2, 1903, the Hights, Dimond, California.
  - Routledge, George, & Sons, 1 autograph note, signed, Oakland, California, 1885(?) (Box 1)
    On a notecard and with printed biographical sketch, corrected, enclosed.
  - St. Nicholas, editor, 1 autograph letter, signed, to the editor, New York, 1883 January 29 (Box 1)
    Submitting a story "Capt. Duck," of which a brief summary in an unidentified hand appears on the verso of the letter.
  - Stedman, Edmund Clarence, autograph inscription written on reverse of a photograph, 1872 June 27 (Box 1)
  - Stedman, Laura Woodworth, 1 autograph letter, signed, Oakland, California, 1912, undated (Box 1)
    Includes miscellaneous material connected with Joaquin Miller including newspaper clippings, postal cards, pictures, pamphlets. From the estate of Stedman.
  - Stedman, Laura Woodworth, from Juanita Miller, 26 autograph letters, signed, and autograph notes, signed, 9 autograph notes signed on miscellaneous cards, 1902-1931; 2 (Box 1)
    Includes photographs, picture-post cards, clippings from magazines and newspapers about Juanita Miller, annotated.
  - Stone and Kimball, 3 autograph letters, signed, from Miller, Oakland, California, 1895 April-July 15 (Box 1)
    Concerning the publication of his The Building of the City Beautiful.
  - Woodward, Fred E., 1 autograph letter, signed, from Miller, Oakland, California, with original addressed envelope, 1911 December 7 (Box 1)
    1 autograph letter signed from Miller to Fred E. Woodward, December 7, 1911, Oakland, California. With original addressed envelope.
  - Unidentified correspondents
    - 1 autograph note, signed, from Miller to unidentified recipient, 1877 December 10 (Box 1)
    - 1 autograph note signed from Miller to "My Dear B", 1893 April 7 (Box 1)
    - 1 autograph letter, signed, from Miller to unidentified correspondent (Carmany?), New York., August 21 (Box 1)
    - 1 autograph letter, signed, from Miller to "My very dear fellow Senlire(?)," Fruitvale, California., 1912 October 11 (Box 1)
    - 1 autograph note, signed, from Miller to "My dear Miss H--", 1899 November 9 (Box 1)
    - 1 autograph letter, signed, from Miller to unnamed correspondent, Dimond, California, 1908 January 28 (Box 1)
    - 1 autograph letter, signed, from Miller to "My dear P.(?)," Washington, 1885 December 6 (Box 1)
    - 1 autograph letter, signed, from Miller to "S.," The Hights, California, 1892 November 18 (Box 1)
      On stationary bearing his printed account of "The Arbor day cross" at top.
- Writings, 1870-1905; Series II; Series II is organized into two subseries: Poetry and Other Writings.
  - Poetry
    - "Alone," autograph manuscript, signed, Boston, one 7-line stanza, 1876 August 17 (Box 1)
    - "By the Sun-down Seas," page proof of pages 1-2 and 9-10, with notes by Miller, "A Picture," proof, 27 lines, with note, signed, 1873 February 27, undated (Box 1)
    - "The Lost Regiments (A Legend of the Late War)," original manuscript, 7 stanzas, undated (Box 1)
    - "New York City," corrected proof, with manuscript title and signature, before 1877 (Box 1)
      A poem of 3 ten-line stanzas, used without title, as epigraph to part 2, "On Fifth Avenue," of his The Baroness of New York (Published G.W. Carlton & Co., 1877).
    - "A Pioneer of Idaho," printer's copy of original manuscript in hand of Ina Donna Coolbrith, with corrections by Bret Harte, before September 1870 (Box 1)
      Published in The Overland Monthly, September 1870, v.5, p.280-286. Published under the title "Rough Times in Idaho."
    - "Rome," manuscript, signed, Chicago, Illinois, one 5-line stanza, with positive photostat, 1875 November 6 (Box 1)
    - "A Sioux Lodge," original manuscript, 10 stanzas, signed, undated (Box 1)
    - "With Walker in Nicaragua," autograph manuscript of prefatory verses beginning "Come to my Sunland," 8 lines, signed, undated (Box 1)
    - "Woman," autograph manuscript, signed, one 8-line stanza, undated (Box 1)
    - Unidentified verse, autograph manuscript, signed, Oakland, one 4-line stanza beginning with the line "Why, I would rather stoop and bear...", 1888 February (Box 1)
  - Other Writings
    - The Building of the City Beautiful, autograph manuscript, in the hand of an emanuensis, with 20 pages in the author's autograph, before 1905 (Box 1)
      Published: Albert Brandt, Trenton, New Jersey, 1905.
    - Unidentified manuscripts in Miller's handwriting, with his signature, undated (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous folio pages and scraps of typewritten and autograph manuscript and notes, 47 leaves, with 2 leaves bearing clipped printed poems, undated (Box 1)
- Other Papers, 1872-1901; Series III
  - Autograph inscription, 1893 July 28 (Box 1)
  - Autograph inscription, Oakland, California, on printed stationery headed: Joaquin Miller Lecture Season, 1900-1901, on verso: photographs of Joaquin Miller at different ages, 1901 March 9 (Box 1)
  - Autograph inscription signed, Boston, 1877 October (Box 1)
  - "Isles of the Amazons," manuscript contract for the publication of poem in The Overland Monthly, signed by Miller, San Francisco, 1872 June 22 (Box 1)
  - Photographs, 1898-1915, undated (Box 2)
    Contains portrait photographs of Joaquin Miller and snapshots of Joaquin and Juanita Miller. Candid photographs include Joaquin Miller hiking in Alaska (1898) and a snapshot his home in Canyon City, Oregon. A series of snapshots show Juanita Miller creating potpourri sachets.
  - Portrait photograph of Joaquin Miller by James E. Purdy, Boston, undated (Box 3)